Guide to the Hiram Corson papers, 1842-1956.
Corson, Hiram papers, 1842-1956.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hiram Corson papers, 1842-1956.
14-12-449
Hiram, Corson, 1828-1911.
4.8 cubic ft.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Thirty scrapbooks containing letters, clippings, photographs, and printed materials relating to Corson's travels, life, and career; correspondence exchanged between Corson and colleagues on Shakespeare, Chaucer, Tennyson, Browning, and other figures of English literature; reviews of books and articles by Corson and other scholars; announcements, programs, letters, notes, and reviews pertaining to Corson's activities as public lecturer and reader; letters from friends and family members dealing chiefly with personal matters: health, progress of career, daily activities; one scrapbook devoted to spiritualism, including letters from and about Madame Helena Petrovna Blavatsky, co-founder of the American Theosophical Society. Unbound material includes large numbers of family letters with extensive comments on the early days of Cornell University and life in Ithaca, New York, accounts of the travels of Corson, his wife, Caroline, and their son Eugene, their daily work and activities; clippings, pamphlets, reprints of articles relating to Corson's work in the field of English literature and that of his son in medicine; drafts of lectures and articles; anatomical, physiological, and surgical drawings; photographs; a syllabus; and miscellaneous books. Also, a tape recorded interview with Signe Sjoegren conducted by Gould P. Colman concerning the activities of Corson during the last seven years of his life.
Correspondents include Louise Andrews, Matthew Arnold, Henry Ward Beecher, Madame Blavatsky, Edwin Booth, Robert Browning, Francis James Child, Mary Cowden Clarke, George William Curtis, Edward Everett, Willard Fiske, Jessie Fothergill, Horace Howard Furness, Frederick J. Furnivall, Daniel Coit Gilman, Samuel Stehman Haldeman, Edward Everett Hale, James Orchard Halliwell-Phillipps, Bret Harte, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Oliver Wendell Holmes, William Dean Howells, Clement Mansfield Ingleby, William James, Pierre Janet, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, James Russell Lowell, John M. D. Meiklejohn, J. Parker Norris, Goldwin Smith, Andrew D. White, Walt Whitman, John Greenleaf Whittier, and Woodrow Wilson.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of English literature.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Thirty scrapbooks containing letters, clippings, photographs, and printed materials relating to Corson's travels, life, and career; correspondence exchanged between Corson and colleagues on Shakespeare, Chaucer, Tennyson, Browning, and other figures of English literature; reviews of books and articles by Corson and other scholars; announcements, programs, letters, notes, and reviews pertaining to Corson's activities as public lecturer and reader; letters from friends and family members dealing chiefly with personal matters: health, progress of career, daily activities; one scrapbook devoted to spiritualism, including letters from and about Madame Helena Petrovna Blavatsky, co-founder of the American Theosophical Society. Unbound material includes large numbers of family letters with extensive comments on the early days of Cornell University and life in Ithaca, New York, accounts of the travels of Corson, his wife, Caroline, and their son Eugene, their daily work and activities; clippings, pamphlets, reprints of articles relating to Corson's work in the field of English literature and that of his son in medicine; drafts of lectures and articles; anatomical, physiological, and surgical drawings; photographs; a syllabus; and miscellaneous books. Also, a tape recorded interview with Signe Sjoegren conducted by Gould P. Colman concerning the activities of Corson during the last seven years of his life.
Correspondents include Louise Andrews, Matthew Arnold, Henry Ward Beecher, Madame Blavatsky, Edwin Booth, Robert Browning, Francis James Child, Mary Cowden Clarke, George William Curtis, Edward Everett, Willard Fiske, Jessie Fothergill, Horace Howard Furness, Frederick J. Furnivall, Daniel Coit Gilman, Samuel Stehman Haldeman, Edward Everett Hale, James Orchard Halliwell-Phillipps, Bret Harte, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Oliver Wendell Holmes, William Dean Howells, Clement Mansfield Ingleby, William James, Pierre Janet, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, James Russell Lowell, John M. D. Meiklejohn, J. Parker Norris, Goldwin Smith, Andrew D. White, Walt Whitman, John Greenleaf Whittier, and Woodrow Wilson.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Corson, Hiram, 1828-1911.; Andrews, Louise.; Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888.; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887.; Blavatsky, H. P. (Helena Petrovna), 1831-1891.; Booth, Edwin, 1833-1893.; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889.; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889 -- Criticism and interpretation.; Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400 -- Criticism and interpretation.; Child, Francis James, 1825-1896.; Clarke, Mary Cowden, 1809-1898.; Corson, Caroline.; Corson, Eugene.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Everett, Edward.; Fiske, Willard.; Fothergill, Jessie, 1851-1891.; Furness, Horace Howard, 1833-1912.; Furnivall, Frederick James, 1825-1910.; Gillman, Daniel Coit.; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880.; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Halliwell-Phillipps, J. O. (James Orchard), 1820-1889.; Harte, Bret.; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.; Ingleby, C. M. (Clement Mansfield), 1823-1886.; James, William, 1842-1910.; Janet, Pierre, 1859-1947.; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882.; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891.; Meiklejohn, John M. D.; Norris, Joseph Parker, 1847-1916.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 -- Criticism and interpretation.; Smith, Goldwin, 1823-1910.; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892 -- Criticism and interpretation.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892.; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1924.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887; Blavatsky, H. P. (Helena Petrovna), 1831-1891; Booth, Edwin, 1833-1893; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400; Child, Francis James, 1825-1896; Clarke, Mary Cowden, 1809-1898; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892; Fothergill, Jessie, 1851-1891; Furness, Horace Howard, 1833-1912; Furnivall, Frederick James, 1825-1910; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Halliwell-Phillipps, J. O. (James Orchard), 1820-1889; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Ingleby, C. M. (Clement Mansfield), 1823-1886; James, William, 1842-1910; Janet, Pierre, 1859-1947; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891; Norris, Joseph Parker, 1847-1916; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616; Smith, Goldwin, 1823-1910; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Andrews, Louise; Corson, Caroline; Corson, Eugene; Everett, Edward; Fiske, Willard; Gillman, Daniel Coit; Harte, Bret; Meiklejohn, John M. D.; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1924; Colman, Gould P. (Gould Patchin), 1926-; Sjoegren, Signe.; Theosophical Society in America.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Cornell University -- History.; Cornell University; Theosophical Society in America
Subjects:
Authors.; English literature.; Medicine.; Spiritualism.; Women mystics.; College teachers.; Authors; College teachers; English literature; Medicine; Spiritualism; Travel; Universities and colleges -- Faculty; Women mystics
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; New York (State) -- Ithaca
Form and Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.; Criticism, interpretation, etc.; History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collection:
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Spiritualism Materials
Series III. General Documents
Series IV. Eugene Rollins Corson material
Series V. Pauline Corson material
Series VI. Photographs
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  Includes letters from Eugene, Pauline, and Caroline Corson. Note: some of the letters were written to Eugene or Mrs. Corson. Many letters refer to spiritualism.
  - Old storage envelopes from correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Expression (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1855-1860; Includes Henry Wadsworth Longfellow letters to Caroline Rollin Corson: March 9, 1855-Regrets his publisher declined the translation on grounds of expense of printing in foreign language. Information about certain poems. Grieved about misfortuen which has befallen them. Hopes her school will flourish; May 15, 1855- Glad she found publisher in N.Y. for "Hyperion" will gladly look at proof sheets; June 15, 1855- Offers use of his name if it will be of any service. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth
  - Correspondence, 1861-1864; Includes Nathaniel Hawthorne letter, dated February 17, 1964: Hawthorne thanks Corson for gift of Chaucer's "Legende of Goode Women" with hopes expressed for American edition of Chaucer's "Canterbury Pilgrims" edited in the same manner. Also includes some printed pamphlets and posters for performances. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Hawthorne, Nathaniel
  - Correspondence, 1865-1866; Includes address of Hiram Corson on occasion of his induction as professor at Girard College. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Everett, Edward
  - Correspondence, 1867-1869; Includes James Russell Lowell letter, dated October 24, 1867, to "my dear child" in which he regrets delay in publishing Mr. Corson's work and gladly would double subscription if it would help. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Lowell, James Russell
  - Correspondence, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1874-01-1874-05; Includes letter from Bret Harte, and letter from Edwin Booth with references to Hamlet. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Harte, Bret
    Booth, Edwin
  - Correspondence, 1874-06-1874-12; Includes printed pamphlets and posters for performances, correspondence on Pauline's death. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1876-01-1876-09 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1876-10-1876-12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1877-01-1877-05 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1877-06 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1877-07 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1877-08-1877-12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1878-01-1878-07 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1878-08-1878-09 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1878-10-1878-11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1878-12 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1879-01-1879-04 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1879-05-1879-12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1881-1882; Includes two letters from Robert Browning: one inviting the Corsons' to lunch and another setting a convenient time to call. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Browning, Robert
  - Correspondence, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1886; Includes a letter from Robert Browning expressing thanks and letter from Walt Whitman sending notes and mentioning Woodruff's visit. Also includes letter from Edward Everett Hale. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Hale, Edward Everett
    Whitman, Walt
  - Correspondence, 1887-1888; Includes land deed and letter from Gabrielle DeVeaux Clements regarding Corson's portrait. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Clements, Gabrielle DeVeaux
    Gosse, Edmund
    Cowden Clarke, Mary Victoria
  - Correspondence, 1889; Includes photograph of Shakespeare's gloves. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1892-01-1892-09 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Tolstoy, Sophie Andreevna
  - Correspondence, 1892-10-1892-12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1894 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1895-01-1895-08 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1895-09-1895-12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1897; Includes letter from Prince Serge Wolkonsky. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Wolkonsky, Serge
  - Correspondence, 1898; Includes letter and poems by Gottfried Hult. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Hult, Gottfried
  - Correspondence, 1899-1900 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1901-01-1901-05; Includes letter to Caroline Corson from Dr. Silas Weir Mitchell. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1901-05 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1901-06-1901-07 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1901-08-1901-12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1902-01-1902-08 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1902-09-1902-12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1903-01-1903-02 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1903-03-1903-05 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1903-06-1903-12; Includes letter, dated November 18, 1903, from Woodrow Wilson congratulation Corson. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Mitchell, Silas Weir
    Haultain, Theodore Arnold
    Wilson, Woodrow
  - Correspondence, 1904-01-1904-05 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Wier, Silas Mitchell
  - Correspondence, 1904-06-1904-12 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1905-01-1905-04 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1905-05-1905-08 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1905-09-1905-12 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1906-01-1906-03; Includes letters from Hiram Corson to Eugene Corson regarding Robert Browning: "On Wednesday evening, I read to my spiritual visitors my reminiscences of Browning, who had asked for them at the previous sitting [i. e., seance]. There were present Ma, Pauline and the boys, Browning, Tennyson, Whitman, Longfellow, J. W. H. Myers, Mrs. Browning, and Mrs. White - eleven in all. I read for an hour and a quarter... Browning did the rapping during the reading... [His]raps were very loud, and sometimes there was a rapid succession of them, which I took to signify a special approval of what I was reading at the time - ... At the close of the reading there were loud raps by Browning which I took to signify his approval of the paper. It will make a chapter in my book of about 25 pages... " A separate letter refers to the seance and mentions that he read them to his "Sage Class" at Cornell. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1906-04-1906-09 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1906-10-1906-12 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Stoneman, Bertha
  - Correspondence, 1907-01-1907-04 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1907-05-1907-12 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1908-01-1908-07 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1908-08-1908-12 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Besant, Annie
  - Correspondence, 1909-01-1909-07 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1909-08-1909-12; Includes last will and testament of Hiram Corson (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1911-01-1911-07 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1911-08 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1911-09-1911-12 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1931 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1956; Includes newspaper clippings and receipts. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Sjoegren, Signe
  - Correspondence, Undated; Includes letter from Fannie Barrett Browning postponing an engagement with Mrs. Corson on account of husband's headache. Also contains newspaper clippings. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Browning, Fannie Barrett
    McGraw Fiske, Jennie
    Osler, William
  - Horace Howard Furnace letters to Hiram Corson, 1872-10-10-1909-06-02 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Joseph Henry, 1850-1871 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters from F.J. Childs and George Allen, 1867-1881 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters and clippings from H.R. Haweis, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series II. Spiritualism Materials
  - Letters from Louisa Andrews to the Corsons, 1874-11-1876-02; Letters concerning spiritualism, merits of various mediums, spread of faith, and Olcott-Blavatsky partnership. Also includes letter to Andrews from JM Roberts calling into question the motives of Helena Petrovna Blavatsky and Henry Steel Olcott. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Helena Petrovna Blavatsky, 1875-1878; Written by Blavatsky to Mrs. Caroline Corson (written in French and referring to Louisa Andrews), Alexander Akozokof introducing Mrs. Corson, and photostat of letter to Hiram. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letter to Madame Blavatsky from J. R. Buchanan, 1875-08-29; Concerning articles on science and religion. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letter to Madame Blavatsky from Francis F. Lippitt, 1875-03-03; Concerning the authenticity of the "materializations" in which Mr. and Mrs. Holmes and Dr. Child were involved; mentions the "deep disgrace" of Katie King; also refers to Professor Corson, Mrs. Andrews of Springfield, and Colonel Olcott. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letter to Madame Blavatsky from S. P. Stephens, 1875-01-30; Concerning alleged spiritualist frauds of Henry T. Child. Refers to a couple named Holmes, to a Katie King, and a Mrs. White. Also signed by Francis J. Lippitt as witness (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Henry Steel Olcott from Emma H. Britten and J. M. Peebles, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letter to Hiram Corson from G.L. Ditson, 1875-10-22 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Hiram Corson from V.A. Taylor, 1876-01-12 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letter to Hiram Corson from Luther Colby, 1876-01-02; Luther Colby, editor of the Banner of Light, accepting for publication an article by Corsonattacking the American Theosophical Society (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Hiram Corson from Emilie G. Jones, 1875; Emilie Jones, sister of Louisa Andrews, reporting on latter's health. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Statement of William H. Westcott, concerning the seances of Mr. and Mrs. Holmes; witnessed by Francis J. Lippitt., 1875-01-31 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letter from David Higham to Eugene R. Corson regarding Blavatsky photographs, 1929-07-19 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clippings and publications on spiritualism and Helena Blavatsky, 1870-1890 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photograph of Helena Blavatsky by Beardsley in Ithaca, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series III. General Documents
  - Clippings, notes, and printed material removed from scrapbook, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - VI Centenaire de l'Universite de Montpelier, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Printings and clippings removed from scrapbook number 1, 1880-1892; Mainly programs and pamphlets relating to lectures or exhibits (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Xerox copy of "A Few Reminiscences of Robert Browning" from the Era, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Fragments of material torn from scrapbook, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Information about Hiram Corson for Who's Who, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Pamphlets and publications (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Clippings from scrapbook number 3, mainly regarding Ireland, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Shakespeare pamphlets and clippings, 1870-1895 (Box 3, Folder 29-31)
  - Printed material from scrapbook number 9, 1860-1870 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Manuscripts from scrapbook number 30, 1887-1890; Includes notes for a course on Robert Browning and clippings of reviews of Corson's book, and Corson's Readings fliers. (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Clippings and documents on Hiram Corson's death and will, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Reviews and comments on "The Aims of Literary Study" by Hiram Corson, 1895-1903 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Article about Robert Browning, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Clippings and printed material relating to Hiram Corson's career, 1862-1911 (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - Clippings and printed material from scrapbook number 1, 1864-1874 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Clippings and articles, 1860-1910 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - University of Dublin Tercentenary, 1892; Includes invitations and programs. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Flier for Hiram Corson lecture, Undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Passport of Caroline Corson, 1878-06-15 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Typescript of Wordsworth's Nature Philosophy, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Draft typescript of Wordsworth's Nature Philosophy, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of Whitman's Song of the Open Road, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Clipping from the Ithaca Journal on Cascadilla Cottage, 1933-12-29 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Etching of Walt Whitman, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Printed sketch of Wordsworth, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Clippings from the Alumni News, 1902 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series IV. Eugene Rollins Corson material
  - Articles written by Eugene Corson, 1881-1903 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Clippings relating to Corson's medical career, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook items, invitations, and general documents, 1867-1905; Includes typescript note from Burt Green Wilder (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Medical drawings, notes, and clippings, Undated; Includes 6 photographs of lepers from San Remo, Italy (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lecture notes, 1869-1872 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Homeopathic Times, 1880-07 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Last Days with my Father manuscript, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Passport, 1878-05-27 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Medical journals, 1877-1916 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly Journal of Medicine, 1911-1913 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Medical drawings, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets written by Eugene, 1890-1916; Includes some scrapbook miscellany. (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Clippings and printed material, 1880-1910 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Medical drawings, 1873-1906 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
- Series V. Pauline Corson material
  - Material from scrapbook number 2, Undated; Includes photographs of Pauline and others, Pauline's autograph book, and greeting cards (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Clippings and documents on the death of Pauline Corson and Caroline Corson, 1874-1902 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Penmanship practice, French practice, and coloring book from scrapbook, Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Drawings from scrapbook number 2, 1855-1874 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Mounted plant speciments, 1855-1874 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Drawings from scrapbook number 2, 1855-1874 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Embroidered bookmarks and small samples from scrapbook number 2, 1855-1874 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Paper dolls from scrapbook number 2, 1855-1874 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Series VI. Photographs
  - Pictures of cathedrals and churches from scrapbook number 5, 1880-1910 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Various friends and acquaintances, 1870-1910 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Signed photograph of Robert Browning, 1889-11-05 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Mary and Charles Cowden Clarke and Charles' home, 1872-1881 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - James Orchard Halliwell-Phillips and wife, and their house in Brighton, England, 1880-1889 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - James Orchard Halliwell-Phillips residence in Brighton, England, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Warren Holden, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Friedrich August Leo, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Horace Howard Furnace, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Edward Dowden, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - William Benham, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Edwin Booth, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Charlotte Bronte, Arthur Bell Nicholls, Patrick Bronte, and Haworth buildings, 1877; All purchased at /Haworth (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Alonzo Curtis Nichols, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Hiram Corson, uncle of Professor Corson, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Hiram Corson, uncle of Professor Corson, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Hotels, abbeys, castles, etc. in Europe, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Hiram Corson and photograph of painting of Caroline Rollins Corson, 1880-1910 (Box 5, Folder 10)